We have here Marlene Mangani. She is
senior devrel at Microsoft. She's a
friend of mine and also a wonderful
voice at the AI ecosystem. Uh and today
she'll be speaking to us about uh a
product a practical guide to agentic
coding. So, please a warm welcome to
Marlene.
>> Hi everyone. Hopefully you can hear me.
Um but yeah, Luis already introduced me.
My name is Marlene. I work at Microsoft.
And at GitHub I work on a team called
Core AI. So, the goal my talk today is
going to be a practical guide to agentic
coding. And the goal of the talk is
going to be to give us some mental
models so that we can understand
different ways to optimize our coding
agents when we're working with them.
Just a note, all of the slides I'm going
to show are at the link that is there on
all the slides.
So, a quick agenda of what we're going
to be covering. We're going to start
with the evolution of AI and coding.
We're going to look at what coding
agents are and something called an
agentic loop.
And then for most of this talk, I'm
going to hopefully speed run through
some demos of like actual things we can
do with coding agents. And then we'll
wrap up with some best practices.
A good question to start with is what
exactly is agentic coding? So,
I think some good context for us is that
a couple of years ago, when we first
started to see AI show up in our code,
it was through code completion. So,
you'd be writing in your IDE and then,
you know, maybe you're typing out a
function and your LLM would look at the
last two or three lines of code and then
make some suggestions and you could
accept or reject those suggestions based
off of, you know, whether you liked it.
And it's kind of similar to how we have
auto complete on our phone.
Then after that,
uh I think about 2 years ago, uh the
labs like Anthropic and OpenAI started
to work on LLMs that were specifically
designed with coding in mind. And so, I
actually remember during that time
seeing that ChatGPT was getting better
with code and I would go to it and ask
it questions or to generate a script.
Then I would run the script in my IDE
and then maybe if there was an error,
I'd copy the error and put it in ChatGPT
and it was kind of this process of going
back and forth, copying and pasting.
Does anyone remember that era? It was a
bit It was a bit tough. Um and but the
cool thing with that era was that it
showed us that
LLMs can actually generate good code and
they can work with us with our code.
And now I want to say about a year ago,
so it hasn't been very long, we really
started to see some agentic coding
workflows. So, for example, at
Microsoft, we
uh created something in VS Code with
GitHub Copilot called Agent mode. And
then when a user starts using Agent mode
or turns it on, Copilot then turns into
this sort of autonomous AI agent and it
can do work on your behalf. So, the
agent is able to run and execute
commands in the terminal, it's able to
carry out multi-step commands for very
long-running processes, and it can also
debug its own code. And I think the key
thing that changed there was that we
gave our agent access to our full
workflow. So, we're still using the the
LLMs that are good at code, but the
difference is that we're giving our
agent access to the right context and
the right tools so that your agent can
make decisions and then also take action
on that on those decisions because it
has access to the tools in your work in
your workspace.
Right now, there are a number of
different coding agents available on the
market today and I would say we're a bit
at an inflection point in terms of the
coding agent. So there's a bit of a
fight in terms of which coding agent is
going to come up on top. I'm a big
Copilot fan. Of course, I work for
Microsoft.
But other people like other coding
agents and the good thing for us as
developers is that it means regardless
of where you want to work with that's in
your IDE, you can use Copilot in VS
Code. If you're working in the CLI, I
know some people, very few people use
Cloud to Code. I'm joking. A lot of
people use Cloud to Code.
Um and then in if you're working in the
web, you can use things like Codex or
Jewels. And then you can also build your
own custom agents. Pydantic AI is a good
example of an SDK that you can use to
build a custom agent. And all of these
agents that are built, they have it's
sort of like
we have something called a harness. So
this is the word that's becoming more
popular these days is you build out this
harness in code that wraps around the
model and it gives the model access to
tools and different context so you can
use things Pydantic AI to be able to
actually build out the harness.
Um one thing I will say is that even
though we have this variety of coding
agents,
we all of them typically work very
similarly under the hood. And I think a
good way for us to understand how we can
get the most from the agents is to
understand how they work.
So
uh where we can start is by answering
the question, what is an AI agent? So,
this question has been debated in the
past, but now I would say a widely
accepted definition is that an AI agent
is an LLM that runs tools in a loop to
achieve a goal. So, this is pretty
widely accepted. And
I would say specifically for coding
agents, this agentic loop that you can
see on the screen is usually what's
associated with coding agents. I
actually got this image
uh or you know, the diagram there from a
blog post by Anthropic where they were
writing about how Claude code works
under the hood. So, you have these steps
here and I would and for the rest of
this talk, we're actually going to walk
through the three steps, gathering
context, taking action, and verifying
results. We're going to look at how we
can optimize our workflows at each step
of these points to be able to get the
best results from our coding agent.
So, we are going to start with number
one, which is gathering context. So,
when you go to your coding agent,
wherever that is, you're going to send
through a prompt and you're going to ask
it to complete a task.
And the first thing your coding agent is
going to do is it's going to try to
gather context, the context it needs to
complete that task. And I would say as a
developer, one of the main things you
want to do is to make sure that your
agent, number one, has access to the
right context, to the right files that
are
will enable it to complete its task and
that it's able to also manage that
context in a good way. So, we'll look at
two examples of this. First thing we can
talk about is you I'm in VS Code right
now
um and this is the chat with Copilot.
So, one way to actually give your agent
context is just to attach it attach it
to the chat. So, if I click on that plus
button, you can see I have different
options. I could attach a a GitHub
issue, a pull request, or I could attach
a file. So, here if I click on GitHub
issues, it's going to automatically
detect the issues that are available on
this repo. So, if I choose this add read
me one and if I say tell me
about this issue.
Then the agent should be able to read
through that context, directly pull in
information from the issue, and then
hopefully in an ideal world, it'll
actually get started working on that.
You'll You'll use the agent to work on
the issue with you.
Another thing to note is that we have
instruction files. So, if you are using
uh GitHub Copilot, these are called
Copilot instructions.md.
If you're using Cursor, they're Cursor
rules. If you're using Claude,
Claude.md. And one that's popular right
now is agents.md.
And if I go ahead and in my chat I just
say hello
to the agent, the agent is going to
respond and say, "Hi, I'm Marlene's AI
assistant for her PiAI talk. How can I
help?" The reason that it knows to
respond in this way is that I have
defined a Copilot instruction file and
it says the instructions in terms of how
the agent should act. So, if I want to
control my coding agent and tell it how
to behave, it's going to be from these
instructions files. And this is sort of
at the repository level.
Another thing that we need to think
about is about
uh context rot or context bloat. And
this happens in terms of uh how much
context you're sending to your agent or
you to your LLM. So, there was a study
done by the team at Chroma that found
that once your agents hit a certain
amount of context or once an LLM has a
certain amount of context in its context
window, the performance is going to
degrade. So, you want to be able to
manage the context that you are giving
your model. If you're using a pre-built
harness, for example, here in Copilot,
we actually monitor how much how many
tokens are in the code in the token
window, and then we'll compact
immediately like if it reaches a certain
threshold. But, if you're building your
own agent, so in this example here, I'm
using Pydantic AI, and I've created this
function here called compact history.
And what will happen is that I've
created an agent for Pydantic, and every
time this agent run, it's going to call
this compact history function. And
what's in the function, what's in the
code here, is that the agent is going to
take in our messages, it's going to
count the total number of tokens that
are currently in the context window. And
then if the tokens are above 500 tokens,
for example, in this case, then it's
going to see that a limit has been
reached, and it's going to retain only
the last two messages. So, it'll compact
down. Obviously, there's other ways of
controlling compaction. You could
include a small model or a cheaper model
that will automatically summarize for
you. And so, I will give a an example,
and I will try to run this code
to show you what it looks like. So,
right at the bottom of my file, I have
these messages here where I'm saying,
"Tell me a fun fact about black holes."
Actually, I'm just going to run the code
the script, and then we'll read it while
it runs.
So, I
ran this earlier.
Uh
Where is command here? I don't want to
have to type it again. Here we go. Okay.
So, when we run the code, it's going to
call the agent, and first ask it to tell
me a fun fact about black holes.
And then after that, it's going to and
it's going to add whatever response is
there to the history. And then after
that, it's going to add the uh
ask it to expand on this topic. And once
it does, it's going to also add that to
the history. And then we'll follow up
with the next question.
Uh but what we can see here is that
after it ran and gave a response to the
second question, we hit our token limit.
So, there were 700 uh tokens in the
context window. And then because of
that, it will only retain the last two
messages. So, this is one way, for
example, that we can think about context
engineering in terms of if you're
creating your own agents uh with Python,
you want to make sure that you're
thinking carefully about this context.
Uh another thing that we want to be able
to do with our coding agents is to allow
them to take action. There's a number of
different ways people do this, but I
would say the primary way I use or give
my agent tools is through MCP. And MCP
is Model Context Protocol. It is an open
protocol that standardize standardizes
how we give context to LLMs. And
my personal opinion is the main way I
have seen MCP being used is to give
tools or to give access to tools that
are from an external third party to your
agents. So, here, for example, if you
want to if you're in a VS Code and you
want to access a an MCP server, you can
just type in @mcp. And then you'll get
this list of vetted MCP servers. And so,
if you install them, they'll be
available as tools. And actually, if we
click on the chat, we see that we have
our coding agents' most uh typical
coding agents today have built-in uh
tools, but we also want to give them
access to these external tools. So, for
example, I have Excalidraw installed
here, and if I want to, I could say,
"Can you use Excalidraw
to
generate an image
that explains
explains MCP."
And then, when I do that, it's going to
look at the tools that it has available
to it. We've given our agent access to
the MCP tool, and we'll see that the
first thing that it does is it ran the
readme tool. And that tool is going to
access context from the Excalidraw MCP
server. And so, we can see that we've
imported all of this context about how
to use the agent can use Excalidraw
different formats or commands that it
can run to actually get things working
with Excalidraw, and then it should,
hopefully, also be able to use a tool
from Excalidraw to generate the diagram.
And there we have it in
our terminal, we can see this very
pretty diagram about Excalidraw here,
which is super nice.
And this is how, in I would say,
this is one way you can use MCP, and
that's directly in a pre-built coding
agent, but you can also use MCP directly
in your code. So, I also have a second
file with Pydantic that also connects to
an MCP server. So, if you want to use
MCP directly in your own agent that you
want to build for yourself, you can use
Pydantic AI. You're going to connect
either to a remote MCP server, or you
can run a local version, and then you
pass in the server as a tool. And so, if
we run this command here,
and I'm just going to run Python.
What did I name it? Pydantic?
MCP agent.py.
And then if I run this,
my question is I was like, what issues
are open in my ACM TikTok repo? So I
gave another talk and I want the agent
to get access. I gave it access to the
GitHub MCP server. So there's a number
of different MCP servers that are
available online. You can just look for
them and that should give my own agent
access to an MCP server. It can look for
information using that server and will
hopefully
give us a response. It's a bit slow.
Maybe it's the engine Oh, there we go.
And then it shows me exactly which
which issues are available on this
GitHub repository. So this is a great
way to bring both in a pre-built coding
agent and also with your own code, bring
in context and bring in tools. Okay. Uh
I Is it a I'm almost done with time.
Okay.
Okay. So that's pretty much I will skip
through One thing that I also wanted to
talk to show was that
it's probably good to verify that your
agent has generated good code. Pi Pytest
Sorry, Playwright is a good way to do
that in a browser. I'll be talking about
Playwright at AI Engineer. So if you
come to my talk on Friday, I'll
demonstrate how you can give an agent
access to a browser so it can
test out your
your your app or the code dynamically. I
also mentioned that there's been a
couple of studies that say if you're
going to be writing things like your
agents.inb or your instruction files and
skills, which give your agent access to
tools, a human should be the one that
writes those files because it improves
the performance of the agent. And
sometimes if the agent writes it itself,
then the performance is actually
degraded. So probably a good place for
humans to get involved. This is probably
where I'm going to stop in case we need
time for questions, but this is pretty
much what we covered today. All right.
Thanks everyone.
>> Thank you. Do you Do you want to take
questions? Do you want to take one
question? So we have time for one
question. Anybody?
>> Hello. Hi.
Yes. Can you expand on the last thing
that you said about
agents.md being written by humans and
not agents? Yeah.
>> Okay.
Yes. I
can expand on that. So there was a study
released I want to say earlier this year
or towards the end of last year that
showed they actually tracked to see what
was the improvement. So when we create
something like an agents.md, we're
creating sort of an a specialized agent.
So we've told it we've given it all this
context that you need to behave in this
specific way. And what they found was
that if we we we had this task that we
wanted the agent to do and we had the
LLM itself generate an agents.md or
generate a skill.md file, then the skill
actually on average the performance of
the agent would be less would be less
good. So if a human created on the other
hand if a human created that skill so it
was
detailed in terms of do this, take this
step, do that step and a human was the
one that curated it maybe with the help
of an LLM, the performance would go up
16%.
Whereas sometimes if an agent created
it, the performance would go down 20%
and actually in one example,
it actually made it so that the agent
spent more time thinking and using more
tokens and so it was more expensive.
So those links on the screen if you take
a picture, that will lead you to the
study that I found.
Does that help?
Okay.
Cool.
>> Wonderful. Thank you so much.
Um
I'm all right.
Thank you.